Welcome everybody, this is Yasir Al-Othifi from Learned Dental Series, and this
is episode we will continue our discussion about diagnosis and treatment
planning in operative dentistry.
Still we are, diagnosing or klin in the topic of clinical examination of dental
caries. Let me first clear that I don't receive fees, compensation, or realities
from the sales of any of the products shown or discussed in this presentation,
and this presentation has not been sponsored by any company, agency, or
organization, and only be prepared for educational purposes.
Also, this presentation is copyright copyright protected and could not be
transmitted by any mechanical or electronic means without prior permission from
the author.
In this episode, still we are, trying to properly diagnose dental caries at, by
different techniques and at different stages. We already finished our, in the
previous episodes, our, part one,
which includes patient assessment and information gathering in terms of
demographic data, chief complaint and its history, medical history, and dental
history.
Then we go forward for for clinical examination, starting with examination of
dental caries, which is the main focus and the main target of our topic in
general, and which is our main interest as operative dentist.
We already finished the traditional techniques including visual examination,
tactile examination, radiographic examination,
and we already discussed the limitations of, traditional techniques in general,
and how to improve the result and sensitivity of these tests including visual
and radiographic examination.
In this episode, we will go forward to discuss advanced caries detection aids.
Let us start with the electronic caries detector.
Electronic caries detectors are mainly based on the fact that sound enamel is a
good insulator, while caries enamel due to porosity created by demineralization,
these pores are filled with fluids such as ions and ions from saliva, which
becomes more conductor to, electric current, insensistive electric current,
okay, that indicate demineralization the demineralization state of your, tooth
structure.
The electronic detector can measure quantitatively any change in enamel
electrical conductivity referred it to demineralization.
That means that the slight drop in enamel resistance values indicates the
presence of early demineralization.
We have in dental market a lot of a lot of, devices, a lot of equipment, all
based on this difference in resistance between the electric resistance between
sound enamel and caries enamel.
All of these are commercially available ones, just we will discuss them in
brief, okay, it's not our topic, we are discussing the main idea, which is a
difference in electric conductivity due to difference in resistance, okay?
One of the system is Vanguard electronic caries detector where the electric
conductivity is expressed in numerical numbers starting from 0 to 9, this scale
indicates that, okay, when the scale increased, indicates that there is increase
in demineralization in your enamel.
Then comes caries meter L, which is the oldest one and the most common one,
which, uses color lights to indicate caries extent, it translates this, electric
conductivity into a colored light, where green light equals sound, yellow equals
enamel caries, orange dentin caries, and red caries reaching to the bulb or the
severity of demineralization are aggressive, okay?
Then come electronic caries monitor, which measures the bulk resistance of the,
tooth tissue when the tooth as a whole, the crown as a whole, showing a drop in
its electrical resistance and increase the conductivity, that means that there
is a caries in a wear or another, okay?
But now, the most recently introduced is what is called caries scan, caries scan
involves the passing of an insensitive level of electric current through the
tooth, identifies the presence and location of your decay.
Also, it includes a light colored light indicators with the same technique as
caries meter.
These photographs showing a different techniques or different devices.
The one to the left is the electronic caries monitor, and that gel, this gel is
an electrolyte that facilitates the transmission of insensitive electric
current,
while the other to the right is the newest one, which is the caries scan and
caries scan, proof.
Then comes another simple technique, which is caries detection dye.
The idea of caries detection dye, okay, is using indicator dye of protein, okay,
which is called non-specific protein dye to stain the organic matrix of less
mineralized dentin.
It depends on the idea that dentin is caries means that dentin is demineralized.
From where did you get this demineralization? This is by extracting the caries,
extracting the hydroxyapatite crystals in between the collagen matrix.
Then your collagen matrix is much more exposed and ready to be infiltrated by
any non-specific protein,
including dye protein.
This is the idea, okay? That's why this diagnostic aid, okay, is helpful for
detecting caries dentin, demineralized dentin with damaged collagen near to that
of the bulb that and this technique is used mainly for removal painless removal
of caries with chemo-mechanical, caries removal techniques like carisolv,
okay?, especially when you are in need to differentiate between affected and
infected dentin.
It only penetrates destructed demineralized collagen matrix of dentin.
Okay?
And this techniques, this technique could be helpful in diagnosis of occlusal
caries lesion, but mostly it is designed to detect the degree of affection of
last layer at near to that to the bulb, at the bulpal floor, when you are
hesitated to take this decision.
You couldn't take the decision either to remove or to leave, this layer of
dentin and exposing the bulb. This technique involves multiple applications and
multiple removal of the lesion, you apply the dye, then you apply your caries
removal gel,
okay, until it already remove or you denaturate collagen, sometimes you are in
need to use a special, round bird to remove this or a special brush coming with
your system.
This is the photograph showing how the dye could could, stain your dentin and
how it is removed after that in the second photo.
And then you reapply the dye again and reapply your caries removing gel until it
is unstained at all, and you are now safe to place your restoration.
Then coming something much more accurate and definite, which is laser
fluorescence or fluorescence technique.
Fluorescence phenomena is defined as exaggerating the reflected wavelengths more
than the emitted wavelengths when you are applying a emitted light with a
specific wavelengths to an object, the reflectance light
having a larger wave lens even reflectance that's why it appears fluorescent.
Okay? And this fluorescence differs from material to another according to its
structure, including tooth structure.
There is no material at this world, okay? That haven't fluorescence, but the
degree of fluorescence it changes changed from material to another.
Okay? That's why the main idea is the intensity of fluorescent light is
proportional to the amount of material that goes fluorescence and accordingly,
there will be a difference between fluorescence of sound tooth structure and
that of caries tooth structure that could be visible by quantitative laser or
by, blue light, intensive blue light.
This is the idea. Then we are playing with light and the amount of reflectance
of tooth tissue including in some cases the bacterial metabolites.
We have two examples or two tools, depending on this idea.
Diagnodent, which uses argon laser fluorescence, okay, quantitative laser or
light fluorescence, quantitative light fluorescence using blue light.
Let us start with Diagnodent. In this technique, the quantity of mineral loss,
okay, in caries lesion could be scored, okay, and could be measured.
Your lesion or the area you are expecting to have a caries lesion is subjected
to argon laser and will emit fluorescence.
This fluorescent is this fluorescent is collimated, okay, and captured by
camera, okay, which showing a difference in fluorescence from healthy tissues or
sound tooth structures to caries tooth structure.
The initial mineral loss of non-cavitated enamel and dentin lesions on buccal
occlusal surfaces, okay, as well as bacterial activity could be measured because
it also plays a great role in detecting the fluorescence of bacterial
metabolites indicating the bacterial activity at your lesion lesion.
Red argon laser is transported through a fiber bundle to a dip of a special
handpiece, okay, and the step is is autoclavable, okay, with different
diameters, okay, placed against the tooth surface.
Then the laser light penetrates the tooth and the difference in fluorescence
between sound and demineralized enamel and the fluorescence of bacterial
metabolites are recorded by device giving a quantitative record
of the existing decay with audible sound, then the resultant will be a
quantitative record in a form of a score
and at the same time audible sound to alarm you that there is something
abnormal.
The intensity of the florescent is displayed as a number, okay? It range is
starting from 0 up to 99, okay?
Zero indicated minimal fluorescent fluorescent and the tooth is sound,
while 99 indicates maximum fluorescence.
Also, the design of this device based on a huge database which compared the
amount of demineralization to the scored number that will be resulted.
That's why the reading could be compared with the reading of healthy tooth
structure, okay, and the difference could be calculated, okay, according to the
database of your device, okay?
A reading of 10 to 20 indicates some enamel softening, that should be monitored.
A reading from 21 up to 99 indicates definite area of decay that required
intervention,
okay, according to the severity is it up to or, near to 20 or near to 99.
The device has two forms, one classical form, okay, and one portable form which
is a new bin design or diagno bin, okay?
The one to the left is the classical one and the two to the right are the diagno
bin.
And the most right one indicating the cover sleeve that is autoclavable to,
avoid, or to prevent cross infection as a means of infection control, and also
this step is autoclavable and your device is supplied with multiple tips,
different in lens and diameter to allow accessibility in different areas.
This schematic diagram showing that the difference between dental explorer and
diagnodent it depends on the argon laser, the laser is a collimated, coherent
light that could not be, divergent light,
is the same as ordinary light, it trans in a straight line.
That's why it could penetrate your fissure to its depth, while your explorer
could not, penetrate the whole fissure, especially if the if your fissure is
wider at its bottom, it may be catch on the top while the caries lesion is still
or it couldn't penetrate the whole fissure while the caries lesion is a starting
demineralization and its activity as shown on the picture to the left, okay,
and the base while at the base of the fissure, while your coherent collimated,
laser beam, okay, could penetrate to this depth and could not be, faded, okay,
light, like ordinary light.
Then the reflectance of this, fluorescent light, the fluorescent of the tissue,
is then come again to your tip, okay, to provide you with either acoustic
signal,
okay, or a digital display.
Let us see or review these photographs, okay, which shows, the tip of your,
diagno pen, okay, and the sleeve to the left side, which is interchangeable,
both of them are autoclavable, okay?
And now you are operating the argon laser, okay, and waiting for the result.
Let us discuss the score produced, okay, the acoustic notification, okay, or the
acoustic beep just alarm you that there is something abnormal and you should
respect your monitor, okay?
What is the digit appear, okay? For fissure caries, if the value is between 0
and 12, then it is considered a healthy tooth substance.
And for proximal caries, the value is between 0 to 7.
Okay? For fissure caries to interpret it by diagnotent as a starting
demineralization, the the values will be between 13 up to 24.
While that for proximal caries to, interpret it or diagnose it as being starting
demineralization, the values will range between 8 up to 15.
This is according to the manufacturer guide supplied with your device, okay?
But if the values are over 25 in fissure caries and more than 16 for proximal
caries, then there is a strong demineralization that indicate immediate
intervention to manage this.
Let us review certain cases, okay?
The one to the left, there is no visible caries, while after diagnosing it with
diagnotent, we discovered a caries hidden at this area detected with
diagenodent, and this is after opening it with round bur,
just it's a an early detection of your caries.
And how much beautiful your conservative design, just cutting the area,
accessing the caries, and all bits and the fissures, even that appears in your,
diagnotent and in this transillumination photograph, okay?
Above, just indicated for bits and the fissure sealant, and this is the case
after treatment, treating the tooth conservatively.
And how much, let us image imagine, how much you conserve a tooth structure.
Case one, showing number one, no caries shown at the first molar.
Also radiographically, there is no radiolucency that could indicate dental
caries,
as you as we discussed before in the previous episodes.
That we are in need for at least 40% demineralization to be radiographically
noted.
But when we use the diagnotent bin, it demonstrated a score of 28, which which
is within the demineralization or within even the active caries stage.
That's why, when the operator trying to gaining access through the triangular
fossa, he discovered this caries at the dentin enamel junction is starting
demineralization, but this demineralization is still not enough
to be interpreted or denoted as, something we couldn't expect, it indicates
aggressive lesion, okay? It's scored 90.
When the operator opens this lesion, as you could see in figure four, okay,
actually it is an aggressive caries lesion, okay?
It may be hidden in radiograph due to superimposition, okay, of other tooth
structure, and also it may be hidden to visual examination because it is to the
lingual and the tooth is much more far posterior
that you couldn't inspect it actually, you couldn't inspect it perfectly.
And the tooth is also restored with bonded restoration as conservative as
possible.
Another one is this first molar, okay, tooth, in the upper and radiograph didn't
show any visible caries involvement due to the demineralization is out
of the zone to be detected or out of the amount to be detected by radiograph or
to be differentiated by radiograph, surely it is less than 40%.
Then in figure 3, okay,
, the diagnodent reveals a score of 31.
Okay? When the operator opens this, distal fissure, okay, he discovered a caries
extended to or near to dentinoenamel junction that needs intervention with
minimal invasive and conservative cavity preparation.
Then comes the other type which acting on the idea of fluorescence, which is
quantitative light induced fluorescence.
The main difference between them is the first is using argon laser fluorescence
and this one is,
using auto fluorescence of each teeth when subjected to light, especially when
it is, in the blue zone.
This device using, intensive blue zone light, okay, that is focused or emitted
to the tooth and measures the auto fluorescence of your subject, okay, which is
different from,
healthy tissues to caries tissues with the same idea.
Then this auto fluorescence is then captured or detected by special intraoral
camera, which produces fluorescent image.
Then the fluorescent image, okay, and the degree of emitted fluorescent
fluorescence will be related to the degree of demineralization, okay, and the
mineral contents of yours, tissues, especially enamel.
Okay? The difference between the fluorescence of sound tooth tissues and that of
caries lesion can be made visible quantitatively by light induced fluorescence
method,
okay, as a quantitative method to diagnose dental caries, okay?
The intensity of demineralization is related to the degree of dark tents you
could see or respect from, the device.
This picture fluorescent image is transmitted into your, computer, and there is
a software system that can process the image to provide you
with quantitative parameters such as the lesion area, the lesion depth, and the
lesion volume.
Just I would like you to note something, okay, and record this note.
Okay? All the advancements in caries detection, either using visual examination,
radiographic examination, advanced caries detection aids or tools, are based on
the development in digital systems and the development in photo processing
softwares.
Okay? And in order to do that, you should feed these softwares with a huge data,
correlate between
the clinical appearance of your caries lesion and the degree of demineralization
and also the histological pattern expected from this image.
Okay? And this is a huge work done by a a great group of epidemiologists, okay,
and cariologists worldwide.
Without this data, okay, and without feeding these softwares by these data,
okay, they could not
run an accurate detection of dental caries using artificial intelligence, okay,
and still up now, any update in these software
for all of the devices discussed in this episode and the other episode, okay,
regarding, improving, visual examination or regarding,
recent advances in radiographic techniques for detection of dental caries,
there is no update unless you have updated data regarding the link between or
the correlation between the clinical appearance, the degree of demineralization
and the histological pattern of your lesion.
Okay? That's why this is one of these devices devices that use software, okay,
software based in based on artificial intelligence
that could locate the lesion area, lesion depth, and lesion volume, okay?
Depending on the correlation between the fluorescence, okay,
and their trials to link it with different characteristics of caries lesion or
different presentation of caries lesion.
These parameters can detect and differentiate the lesions at a very early stage,
okay, and make qualitative light fluorescence system more sensitive to changes
of caries over a time, okay?
To uses blue light in a range of 488 nanometers to illuminate the tooth, which
normally fluorescent a green color at this range of light,
okay? But the tooth should be dried perfectly to neglect the effect of saliva,
okay, in fluorescence, because if you don't try it perfectly, then the coming
fluorescence
is the fluorescence of saliva including the debris and its proteins, okay, and
the tooth structure.
That's why you should perfectly, perfectly dry the tooth and before drying the
tooth, it is preferred to
polish it and scale it, okay, or scale scaling and polishing.
Okay? But the problem it cannot differentiate between
decay and hypoplasia because both of them are loss of minerals, okay? It only
detects auto fluorescence fluorescence of the lesion of the tooth,
okay? That indicates demineralization or or lower mineral contents of this
structure.
And that's why still you are in need for other clinical investigations, okay?
To, to to to have an an accurate decision about the detection and diagnosis of
your caries lesion, okay?
Because this is also a device, okay, that measurement is only limited, okay, to
several hundred micrometers from the surface which is responsible for
the auto fluorescence of the tooth structure.
Up till now, this device could not access the interproximal area, it's only for
occlusal area.
Okay? In contrast to that of diagnotent, diagnodent having already
interproximal, tips that could access the interproximal area, okay? And this is
the device of, quantitative light induced fluorescence,
okay, which is connected to your CPU, and this is the handpiece which emits the
light in the blue zone, okay, and at the same time, having an intraoral camera,
inside.
Okay? Then comes, a case where you have these teeth in the figure A, okay?
It seems to be absolutely sound, it seems to be absolutely, healthy, okay?
When we already examine it with white light image, okay, and, this, quantitative
light fluorescence,
okay, you could notice a cervical darkness which includes which denotes or
indicates cervical mineral loss,
okay? And after improving the oral hygiene after treating the patient for six
months with fluoride and, oral hygiene program,
okay, then another, image, fluorescent image is taken by the same device,
and you could compare and contrast between B and C, the degree of darkness is
much more lesser.
Then comes critical question, I think all of you are thinking about it, okay?
As being a professional restorative dentist, as being a professor of operative,
dentistry,
which of these advanced devices and which of these advanced technologies, either
advancements in visual examination, either advancements in radiographic,
examination, and now these advanced devices for detection of dental caries,
which of these devices do you prefer?
Okay?
I would like answer to answer you that this is
not the question.
The question the question, for whom
could I use one of these technologies?
Actually, I couldn't relay on one of these unless I have a full record of the
patient, okay, many years ago.
But the question is, when the patient did come to your clinic? This is the
problem.
Okay? How many patients are keen for regular examination of their teeth, okay,
before complaining from any aggressive problem?
This is the question. The majority of our patients, especially in dental
colleges, as they provide,
free service or free healthcare services for most of the patients, okay? And
even in our Arab and Egyptian, countries,
up till now, we don't have the patient which having the mentality and the
culture for regular checkup without complaining.
Not only in dentistry, in all the health surfaces, okay? That's why mostly
of, or most of our patient, 99% of our patient coming with you with visually
obvious caries lesion
that you could inspect a cavitation.
It is not hard for us as being in Egypt or in Arab countries, in this culture,
okay? It is not difficult for us to examine caries visually by simple methods.
Even we don't need explorer, okay? Just only the most helpful one who's caries
detection dye.
Why? Because most of caries are deep, okay? We needed to differentiate between
affected and infected dentin, whether to remove the last layer or not to remove
the last layer.
And we don't need to complicate the treatment in expense of, okay? We could
improve the oral hygiene because this is depends on also on attitude of patient.
Still, up till now, caries risk assessment is much more beneficial for us, we
could gain too much information for it, okay? For me,
if I have one of these recent devices, the only patients that I could apply it
for them is my kids because already as being a dentist, I'm daily inspect or
weekly at least I am inspect their teeth, this is my interest and those are my
kids,
okay? The only two, okay, my son and my daughter, okay? That's that's it, okay?
Otherwise,
okay, I don't know when the patient come to me.
Okay? Unless we have the concept of, checkup every three or six months, even
when we go for caries risk assessment and we advise the patient
to, revisit us, okay, for, reevaluation every three or every six months, this
will not happen.
This didn't happen at all, okay?
What is the percent of of people or patients who will follow your instructions
to that extent
and they are keen to follow it to that extent?
That's why, okay, I didn't use, any one of these not because they are not
beneficial, no.
It's the great devices, great techniques for detection of early caries lesion,
but the question is when the patient could came to you, could come to you for
diagnosis.
This is the question. Finally, those are, the text, books I used in preparing my
presentation,
okay? Please feel free feel free to ask me at any time as your questions are
welcome, okay, just comment to this video and I will reply to your, questions by
comment as soon as possible.
And those are my contact on info, when you would like to contact me.
Finally, I would like to thank you to assign this time to listen to me, please
don't forget to subscribe to my channel and activate notification to get all the
new episodes.
Thank you.
Yasser Al-Nasif.